<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A faithful vvarning to all backsliders, who hold the truth in vnrighteousness, for to return to the Lord and cleave to the light which leadeth out of darkness</title>
            <author>Tompkins, Anthony, d. 1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62880</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1829</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10283</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12590669</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12590669</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63901</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62880)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63901)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 676:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A faithful vvarning to all backsliders, who hold the truth in vnrighteousness, for to return to the Lord and cleave to the light which leadeth out of darkness</title>
                  <author>Tompkins, Anthony, d. 1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Anthony Tompkins.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:63901:1"/>
            <head>A Faithfull VVARNING TO ALL BACKSLIDERS Who hold the <hi>Truth</hi> in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs,</hi> FOR To return to the Lord and cleave to the <hi>Light</hi> which leadeth out of <hi>Darkneſs.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is now in my heart to diſcover unto you the manner of my falling from the Truth, notwithſtanding I had taſted of the Lords Love and did come in meaſure to ſee what was laid up for them that love him in his appearance.</p>
            <p>VVH<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the time of Trials came on that the Lords Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were carried to Priſon, the reaſoning part got up in me, the which the Enemy ſoon joyned with; ſhewing me the danger that might happen if I went to Meetings that then I ſhould or might be put into a Priſon: then, as I ſaid, the reaſoning part got up; inſomuch, that I began to take care for my Wife, and Children, and Family, conſidering the weak capacity of my Wife, ſhe being altogether uncapable of mannaging my Trade, it muſt of neceſſity fail; which Friends, I would have you to take notice, this was whilſt the reaſoning part was gotten up, which, when that began firſt to enter, if I had ſtood in that which did diſcover it not to be of God, my heart had been kept clean; but joyning to the evil, that cauſed the Lords Preſence to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn: 
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63901:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>then did the Devil transform himſelf into an Angel of light, ſhewing me, that Friends did not do ſo well as the <hi>Infidels</hi> did; for they took care of their Families: then the thoughts of this began to miniſter to me a falſe peace; inſomuch, that I became one that did weaken the weak, and to lay a ſtumbling-block in their way: ſo then, when I had done this, yet had I no peace, but was ſtill condemned in my Conſcience: then the transformed Angel had another way ſignifying to me, that I might be ſerviceable in my b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng forth of Priſon, for I might go and ſerve the Body of Friends, which did for a little while ſatisfie; but yet the Lords Love was ſuch, that he ſhewed me that was not enough, but had I ſhould go to the Meetings, and bear my Teſtimony for God, who cauſed the Light to ſhine, and had ſhined into my heart, which gave me to underſtand my duty towards God and man a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d walked in it and obeyed it. But when I had thoughts of obeying the Will of the Lord, then would my Wives tears flow from her eyes, which drew me to be tender to her; and not ſtanding in the Croſs, I came more and more to loſe my portion: Then the Devil drew me to acquaint my ſelf with thoſe that did alſo flee the Croſs, and we began to daub our ſelves with untempered Morter, and ſo grew light and vain, and ſo come to ſpeak our own words, and to think our own thoughts, and to do our own work, and ſo become rebelious Children unto him that was our Father whilſt we obeyed the Light in our hearts, which ſhewed our duty towards God; but we re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſing to obey it, the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my came amongſt us, and ſowed his ſeed; and ſo here was a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in us for victory: inſomuch, that we, or I had no peace, but continually filled with trouble at the very time when I was jeſting and jearing, the Light in my heart did condemn me; and at my lying down, or at my riſing up I was ſo condemned; that I had ſome breathings towards the Lord for to deſire forgiveneſs, and was ready to cry unto the Lord, <hi>Father, forgive me;</hi> but before the word [Father] was uttered, the Lords Witneſs would ariſe in my heart, and ſhew me that I was not to call God Father, for I had done the will of the Devil; which cauſed me to remember what was ſaid of ſome that was calling God Father, and was doing the works of the Devil, and I was out of the redeemed ſtate, as well as they: but as for my dealing amongſt men, I have very little to charge my ſelf with, but can truly ſay, as to that point, I kept my ſelf very
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63901:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>much unſpotted of the World; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſplaid had ſome reſpect for the ſame of the Truth, and could not endure to hear the Truth evil ſpoken of, although I was in a great meaſure departed from it.</p>
            <p>So by my plain dealing among men I was eſteemed with many up and down the Country, my name was famous; inſomuch, that my Trade did much increaſe, ſo that I came to be very much hurried in the World, which did choak the Seed more and more, and ſo became worſe and worſe; ſo the god of the World blinded the mind, that when I would have done the will of God, ſomething or other lay in the way which did hinder; ſo Death and Darkneſs came to reign and to rule and have the preheminence; inſomuch, that the Light which did ſhine once in me, came to be darkned: ſo then that wicked Prince began to reign over the Seed, and kept it in bondage, which would have reigned over the Devil, had it been obeyed as it ought to have been; for I could, and did witneſs it ſo once, but by diſobedience I became a Captive to the Devil, to do his will in a great meaſure. But yet, had there not been a Seed, (I may ſay) I might have been as <hi>Sodom,</hi> or made like unto <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrah;</hi> but I can ſay I was kept out of the practice of many things, which at ſome times was almoſt or altogether concluded in my mind to act: therefore who is like unto the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the God of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> who left us a Seed, or elſe what had become of me in this apoſtatiſing ſtate.</p>
            <p>When I was firſt convinced of the Truth and Living Way, then accounted I all but droſs and dung in compariſon of Chriſt, the Way, the Truth, and the Life; inſomuch, that the Lord was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to manifeſt himſelf unto me in his Way, which was by Chriſt the Light that lighteth every one that comes into the World; ſo as I come to the Light of Jeſus, I come to ſee that I had done amiſs in giving money to the Pariſh Prieſt, whoſe Doctrine I could not own. I had been a hearer of thoſe people called <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> before I came to hear Truth declared by the Servant of the Lord <hi>Edward Borough;</hi> at which time when I went to hear him, I went not to hear (the deſpiſed people, called Quakers) ſo as to receive their Doctrine, but rather gaze at them to ſee their manner: when I firſt came in he that went with me ſeemed to be very much diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with what my dear Friend layed down, for which cauſe he ſpake unto me; my anſwer was to him, I had heard nothing but what
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63901:3"/>was truth, at which time I come away when the Meeting was part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (or the Friends one from each other) with joy, which I knew not how to expreſs; but coming to a Relations houſe, I declared to the Woman that I had heard the Truth declared, and that I did never know the way to which I could witneſs ſatisfaction, but in this Way; which was, that there was the Light of Chriſt in the Conſcience which did diſcover to man his thoughts; (with many words more uſed) inſomuch, (in the time that I was ſpeaking) ſhe was in the mind to hear them, but after I was gone her own wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom got up, and ſo could not become a Fool that ſhe might be wiſe: So after a little time, as I came to depart from committing of ſome ſins I became a prey; he that was like to begin with me firſt was the Prieſt of the Pariſh, whoſe name was <hi>Cooper,</hi> a <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian</hi> counted; his threats cauſed ſome fear to ariſe in my wife, who did make it known to her Siſter, on which they conſidered a way how to keep me from ſuffering, which was, they would pay the Prieſt, and my Wife ſhould pay them again; which thing did continue obſcure for a time hid from me; but my Brother-in-law buying ſome Goods of me, did (when I came to reckon with him) ſtop ſome of my money, which it is like I might diſlike; but at laſt it become cuſtomary to me to do it for a time; but in the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance hereof I found my ſtrength decay, more lighter and vain I grew; and at laſt upon ſome difference he refuſed to pay the Prieſt any longer; inſomuch, the Prieſts man (who gathered money for the Prieſt) came unto me, and did acquaint me what this perſon had ſaid, which was, that he would not pay the Prieſt for me; when that this come before me, in haſt, (being led captive at the Enemies will) he quickly transformed himſelf into an Angel of light, and did ſignifie to me that it was but under-hand dealing, and that I might more lawfuller do it with my own hand; alſo the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, to cauſe me to perform this work, ſhewed me the actions of ſome (that were eſteemed Friends) in that buſineſs, and in other things alſo, the which ought not to have been minded; for he that leadeth out the mind is the Enemy, the ſame that ſhewed me, that it did appear the more lawfull in doing it with my own hands; but as Friends are kept to the true Light, even the Light of Jeſus, they will come to ſee, and to divide between ſpirit and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that is to ſay, between the Spirit of Chriſt and the Spirit of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63901:3"/>Antichriſt, as they continue faithfull to the meaſure of Light they have received; but if that any grow weary of well doing, and ſo become ſlouthfull and ſluggiſh, then comes the Enemy and ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Tares; which if I had continued in diligence to have made my calling and election ſure, then had I anſwered the will of the Lord; for the end of Gods Love in giving his Son a Light into the World, was, <hi>that all men through him might be ſaved:</hi> Therefore I warn all to follow the Light, <hi>that ye may become children of the Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet more I am to acquaint ye with, as touching the former, how, the Lord did appear unto me at laſt after I had reſiſted his Will for years paſt, yet the Lord who is full of compaſſion, whoſe mercy endureth, whoſe Love is never to be forgotten by me; if ever forgetfulneſs ſhould enter again, I muſt never look God in the face more, who hath helped me when I ſaw no helper in the Earth, then did the Lord appear in two of his Stewards whom he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted this charge unto, for to ſpeak unto me, and to lay this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, that I did not do the thing that was right in paying the Prieſt; withal ſignifying unto me, that I did it through fear of him, the which the witneſs for God in my Conſcience did bear him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, that what he ſaid was true; alſo he ſignified to me the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why he ſaid I was afraid, which was true; for I was afraid, otherwiſe I had never paid him, but meerly for fear of man whoſe breath is in his Noſtrils: Alſo my Friend did lay before me, that the Prieſt was one of thoſe that the Prophet of the Lord cried out againſt, that would prepare war againſt thoſe that put not in their mouthes; the Witneſs of God in me did bear him record, that what he ſaid was true; but the Enemy began to rage in me, and (to ſtand in defiance of the Friends words) he did adviſe me, putting me on, and bidding me to charge him to mind his Trade, and let me alone, for he was worſe then he ſhould be as well as I; the Friend would have known what I had to charge him with, but away I ſhuffled; but Gods Witneſs I could not flee from, but it did condemn me that night, and in the morning, but ſtill the Devil did ſtrive to keep the Seed in bondage: I think the day following, or ſoon after came another Friend to me in ſome buſineſs, and whilſt I was talking with him, the Lord, who is the Author of all good, from whence it doth ſpring, cauſed him to open his mouth unto me charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me concerning paying the Prieſt Tythes, &amp; ſaid, he was lately at a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63901:4"/>Meeting with ſome Friends, and there he heard them relate things againſt me that did grieve his heart, (laying his hand on his breſt) which did ſmite me; but ſtill the Roaring Lion was ready to act his part, ſignifying to me, that I ſhould charge him, and ſound him, whether he was not faulty in the ſame thing; he replied, he never did pay the Prieſt a penny, notwithſtanding the Prieſt (I think) would have received the value of a Pint of Sack; what then, (ſaid I) haſt not thou done, as ſome others have done, given the Goaler a Bribe to be thy Friend? thus the Enemy did ſtill endeavor to keep me by his cunning, but the Witneſs of God in my Conſcience he reached, I could not have any peace, but ſtill was diſquieted all that nigh, whilſt I was awake, in the morning I was alſo troubled, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, that I ſpoke to my wife, whoſe love is great towards me, though not of capacity to determine of many things; the Enemy cauſed me to ſtear a new way, laying before me, and her alſo, that becauſe ſhe never had contended for the Truth, therefore ſhe might pay the Prieſt when the man come to demand it; this was concluded it ſhould thus be, and this did miniſter a falſe peace, which laſted but a little while; for I haſtning to the Meeting at <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonſhire-houſe,</hi> as I was going the Witneſs of God did awaken me, and ſhewed me, that I had made a bad mornings work, in making ſuch a concluſion to pay money to him, when I knew it to be contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Truth, and therefore ought not to have been done; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that I was fain to deal plainly with my ſelf, the Lord in his Love did appear unto me in his power and might, and ſhewed me that he was not to be mocked, for ſuch as I ſowed, ſuch muſt I reap; therefore I found I ſhould not flatter my ſelf any longer, but deal plainly with my own Soul, that I might not be cheated of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance that is layed up for all thoſe that love Gods appearance: Then was my hard heart broken, tears falling from my eyes, and then felt the power of God ſtrong in me, which did begin to work out the evil thing that was concluded ſhould be carried on in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents ſubtilty; there did the Lord work in me juſt like unto a man that is removing his houſhold goods, though I had been ſo traitor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to his Light, and had caſt his counſel behind my back, although he gave me precept upon precept, and line upon line: Oh, what a God have I, a God full of mercy whoſe mercies endureth for ever. When the Meeting was over I came home, and as I ſat at dinner
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63901:4"/>with the reſt of my Family, I could ſcarcely for bear weeping, and fell to admoniſhing them, bearing my teſtimony againſt my ſelf, for being negligent in the work of the Lord, alſo did encourage them to go to our Meeting, and alſo ſpoke unto my Wife to go, who ſoon did ſubmit to my deſire, and did go with me; whilſt <hi>I</hi> was in the Meeting <hi>I</hi> was very much broken, tears would have flowed from my eyes, but being among thoſe that knew me, <hi>I</hi> fled the croſs in that, and did ſtrive very much to forbear, and did all the time of the meeting with much ado, which did hinder the Lords work which he had begun afreſh in me; but when <hi>I</hi> came to ſignifie to my wife that <hi>I</hi> was to go forth, (along with the Lords people) the garb ſhe was in cauſed me to be aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and confounded in my ſelf, conſidering once the hopeful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that ſhe was in, which was, ſhe had imparted with her Rings, and pluckt of Lace, and layed by many things; this come to be layed before me, and the Witneſs for the Lord in me ſhewed me theſe things had not been, had <hi>I</hi> kept faithfull to the Lord: So that this did ſo work upon me, that though <hi>I</hi> had reſiſted the Will of God in the Meeting, yet when <hi>I</hi> was coming out of it <hi>I</hi> could not hold any longer, but broke forth into tears to the view of ſome, although <hi>I</hi> would have hid it. <hi>I</hi> could not, but did cry louder then ordinary, and ſo <hi>I</hi> continued ſhedding of tears as <hi>I</hi> went along the ſtreet, and did ſtrive to hide them from my wife, but could hardly do it; who is like unto our God, which plucked me as a Brand out of the Fire? what can <hi>I</hi> do whereby <hi>I</hi> may requite his Love? ſhall not <hi>I</hi> be given up in his will to bear my teſtimony amongſt his people, if it be required of me? yes verily, and ſhall <hi>I</hi> ſacrifice my ſelf and all that <hi>I</hi> have unto the Lord for his Love, which is never to be forgotten; oh, praiſes and glory be unto him for ever, and for evermore, who hath called me out of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into his marvellous Light, who did appear unto me in the night, of Darkneſs, and cauſed his Light to ſhine, in which the power is witheſſed, in which the victory is obtained; oh, praiſes be unto thee my God, who art God of Gods, and Lord of Lords, who by thy Light, Life and Power did reach unto me in a needfull day, and in a time of trouble; what ſhall <hi>I</hi> render unto thee, thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving and obedience for ever: for thou needeſt not any outward
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63901:5"/>thing that <hi>I</hi> have; therefore how ſhall <hi>I</hi> anſwer thy loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? Lord, thou knoweſt the ſecrets of all hearts, thou knoweſt my ſimplicity, thou knoweſt the very end of my writing it in love to all that have backſlidden, to encourage them to return un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Father: all that have been Prodigals as well as <hi>I,</hi> return, <hi>I</hi> can aſſure you, in my Fathers Houſe there is Bread enough, and to ſpare: <hi>I</hi> warn all to return to the Father, who willeth not the death of any, but that all might live; therefore be encouraged whilſt it is day, for otherwiſe the night will overtake you, when it will be too late; therefore, <hi>whilſt it is to day hear his voice, and do not harden your hearts towards to the Lord; why will ye die? I</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, return, put not the day afar off; who knoweth how ſhort our time may be here in this World? <hi>Seek the Lord while, he may be found, call upon him whilſt he is neer;</hi> for he hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us his Servants, <hi>that he will not always ſtrive with man,</hi> whom he hath given precept upon precept, and line upon line, here a little, and there a little. Friends all, conſider your latter end, and the length of time that is after we come to lay down the body into the duſt: alſo conſider, that whilſt ye do abide here, you have no peace here, but a falſe peace, <hi>For there is no peace to the wicked ſaith my God:</hi> But, ye Backſliders, <hi>I</hi> direct my words unto you whom the Lord committed of his hidden Treaſures, whom the World knoweth not; <hi>I</hi> ſay, <hi>I</hi> direct my words chiefly unto you, that you might come to anſwer the Will of the Lord, that ſo you may come to have an Inheritance among them that are ſanctified; you are often in my thoughts, a pity doth ariſe in my heart towards you; I beſeech you return to the Light, and walk in the Light, that ye may come to enjoy fellowſhip with the children of God; oh, the height, the depth of the Love of God, my tongue cannot expreſs what is in my heart towards you: return, I beſeech you, come to a true ſearch, do not heal nor cover your ſelves with falſe coverings any longer, but turn your minds inward, &amp; <hi>commune with your own hearts, and be ſtill;</hi> ſeparate your ſelves from thoſe external things, that you may come to inherit a portion of internal things; that ye may come to enjoy the Crown that is laid up for all thoſe that fear him: but this is my teſtimony for the Truth of our God, that none ſhall come to enjoy the Crown, but as they come to take up the Croſs, and thy
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63901:5"/>own will deny, and ſubject it to the Will of God, for that is the way to obtain a better inheritance then the Kings of the Earth enjoy, which hath not an inheritance that will never fall, a Crown immortal; Earthly Crowns will fall from the head, but this Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Crown will never fall world without end: Oh, Friends; do not ſell your Crown for a meſs of Pottage; do not ſell the Lords Inheritance to Eternity, for an inheritance in the Earth, which none knoweth how little while they may enjoy it: Oh, conſider, I ſay again conſider, the Lords Love is to you, the Lord hath open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Treaſures of Love unto you through me his Servant; who am given up in the Will of the Lord to ſerve him, and to follow the Lamb whitherſoever he leadeth.</p>
            <p>Oh, Lord God of Heaven and Earth, my Soul doth praiſe thee, thy Name is to be honoured by me, who hath done great things for me, who was as it were wallowing in my blood, then didſt thou appear and ſhewed me, that I was as the Prodigal was, that had ſpent his portion upon Harlots in adulterating from the Lord; alſo ſhewed me that there was Bread enough in thy Houſe; thou Lord ſpoke unto me, to the informing of me, juſt as a man doth his Friend, all but the ſound of the tongue: Oh, what a Father have I, what a God have we that pardoneth ſin and tranſgreſſion in us, though we have rebelled and done deſpite to his Spirit of Grace in reſiſting it in its appearance, which would have taught us to have denied all ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and to have lived godly and righteouſly in this preſent world: Oh, Lord, thy Love is never to be forgotten; what ſhall ſeparate thee from us O Lord? ſhall tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation? ſhall perſecution? nay, Lord, in thee is my ſtrength, thou art my Captain, thou haſt gathered me from off the barren Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, thou haſt pluckt me out of the horrible pit, out of the mire and clay, thou haſt ſet my feet upon a Rock, thou haſt eſtabliſhed my goings, this can I ſay; Lord, thou knoweſt the Covenant that I have made with thee, it is in thy Wiſdom I write, and in thy Stength; of my ſelf <hi>I</hi> cannot do it; but thou art my chief Captain, thou art my Strength, thou art my Fortreſs; therefore <hi>I</hi> give thee the glory, who is worthy of all thanks, all the praiſe for ever.</p>
            <p>When thou cameſt unto me as <hi>I</hi> lay upon my bed, thou didſt ſhew me that there was yet a door of Mercy open if <hi>I</hi> would return, did it not then ariſe in my heart, <hi>Speak Lord, thy Servant heareth;</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:63901:6"/>glory be unto thee, who hath cauſed the Light of thy ſelf to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in me, who was in bondage to ſin, and to the power of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which is the Devil, who is the God of the World, and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in the children of diſobedience; praiſes be unto thee whoſe preſence is with me, who art my Strength, and doeſt put me upon this great work, which is of weighty concernment; for there he many Gazers at me, and us, who are wiſe in the comprehending part; they would be glad to have me to write my own words; but I am in the Will of my God, who is my Guide, who leadeth me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Truth; not to write any thing that is in my own will, but what I do is in the will of the Lord; inſomuch, that the mouthes of ſome will be ſtopped, which otherwiſe would be apt to ſay <hi>I</hi> did it in my own will, to be ſeen of men; but the Lord knoweth my heart; <hi>I</hi> have no reſervation at all in my mind, but that my God may be glorified, and my Soul comforted and ſtrengthened, that <hi>I</hi> may never grow faint or weary, but ſtill preſs forward toward the mark which is ſet before me, which is the end of Gods calling me out of darkneſs into his marvellous Light; and this doth ariſe in my heart, that whither ſoever theſe lines may come, which were written in the fear of the Lord, and in obedience unto his Name, that they be not read in a mind that is filled with prejudice, let all of that be removed, as it is out of me at the writing hereof; the Lords Love is raiſed in me, which doth cauſe me to write, to inform all, that there is yet a day of mercy held forth for all that will come out from among thoſe that are reſiſting the Counſel of the Lord, yea, thoſe that reſiſteth his Will, and are doing the will of the Devil. <hi>I</hi> bear my Teſtimony for the Lord, there is yet a day of mercy, <hi>If you will return unto him, he will return unto you, and he will heal your backslidings, and remember your ſins no more:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be encouraged, for <hi>I</hi> was as bad as ſome of you, yet the Lord hath appeared to me by his Light, which never conſenteth to ſin, this, as is heeded and obeyed, it will lead unto the Father; <hi>For none cometh unto the Father but by the Son, who is the Way, the Truth and the Life; nor doth any come unto the Son but whom the Father draweth;</hi> So in love to all have <hi>I</hi> took my pen in hand, who am of my ſelf altogether inſufficient; <hi>but God hath hath hid thoſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and hath revealed them to Babes and Sucklings,</hi> that his Name may be glorified, and your Souls com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63901:6"/>for ever; praiſes be unto my God for ever and for ever, world without end, Amen ſaith my Soul. And by me this is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the ſimplicity of my heart, without any ſelf end, the Lord knoweth my heart; therefore let all be carefull of ſpeaking evil of what they know not, leſt in ſo doing they ſhould offend: This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all I find of neceſſity to write at this time, <hi>I</hi> reſt in the Love of my Father, who hath in meaſure begotten me again unto himſelf, and hath cauſed me to make a covenant with him, never to leave him, but to follow him through good report, and through evil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, knowing that <hi>I</hi> ſhall reap if <hi>I</hi> faint not; for it is <hi>they that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to the end that ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This in pure love to all who are yet reſiſting the Light in their Conſciences, to warn them to return, whilſt it is day, for it is to day if you will hear the Lords voice in you, harden not your hearts, as they did in the old World, who lived in pleaſure, marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and giving in marriage till the Flood came and ſwept them away, all but <hi>No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ah</hi> and eight perſons, as the Scriptures of Truth doth declare. <hi>Oh, Father, who is ſufficient for theſe things, I could not do this without thy Preſence, without thy Counſel, without thy aſſiſtance; Lord, take thou the glory, who art worthy of all,</hi> (and none beſides thee) <hi>of all praiſes and thankſgiving now and for evermore, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Written in the true fear of the Lord,</dateline>
               <signed>by me his Servant, Anthony Tompkins.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>The 2d day of the 11th Moneth, 68.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
